Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project records, 1869-1969 C105
Indiana University Archives
Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project records
1869-1969
1953-1965
Indiana University Archives
Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project
C105
3 cubic feet
Collection consists of 3 cubic feet of records created by Charles F. Voegelin and Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin for their Great Lakes - Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project. Prominently featured in the collection are correspondence and reports prepared for the U.S. Dept. of Justice.
Access Restrictions
The Appointments and Tenure folder in box 3 is restricted.
Advance notice is required.
Historical Note
This project was funded by the US Department of Justice and directed by Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin. The task of the project was to research early records to determine the locations and migrations of the indigenous inhabitants of the Great Lakes and Ohio Valley region during the period that Europeans first moved into the area. The information was used in cases before the Indian Claims Commission. The project started in June 1953 with a 3 year contract and was extended numerous times through 1967.
It was originally headed by Charles F. Voegelin, but the principal researcher was Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin who later was named as the director. It was loosely associated, at least in the beginning, with the Department of Anthropology, but it seems to have been fairly independent during most of its existence.
Scope and Content Note
These files are the administrative files of the project. They contain mostly correspondence regarding the project and reports prepared for the United States Department of Justice.
The Correspondence series, arranged chronologically, has been broken down into several sub-series which define the entity being written to. Some of these sub-series have been arranged alphabetically. Sub-series include correspondence to the United States Department of Justice, Co-operation, Report Required, and a miscellaneous sub-series with assorted correspondence.
The Reports series is arranged alphabetically and deals with reports sent to the United States Department of Justice. There is one sub-series regarding research trip reports.
The Subject files series has been arranged alphabetically. One file, Appointments and Tenure, 1954-60 is closed to research due to the sensitive material contained within. Contact the university archivist for more information.
The Financial materials series is a representative sampling of the original records contained in this collection. When the collection was originally processed half a dozen folders were selected that covered the bulk dates of the financial materials. The remaining financial documents where determined to not have any historical significance and were discarded. The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: 1) Correspondence, sub-series: Justice Department, sub-series: Co-operation, Sub-series: Report Required, sub-series: Miscellaneous 2) Reports, sub-series: Research Trip Reports 3) Subject files 4) Financial Materials
Separated Material
One box of books was sent to the Mathers Museum on 18 Feb 1994.
Two boxes of financial records were discarded at time of processing.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0485.
Fieldwork.; Indians of North America --Great Lakes Region --Migrations --Research.; Indians of North America --Ohio River Valley --Migrations --Research.; Indians of North America --Great Lakes Region --Research.; Indians of North America --Ohio River Valley --Research.; Ethnohistory --Great Lakes Region --Field work.; Ethnohistory --Ohio River Valley --Field work.; Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project -- History -- Sources; Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project -- Records and correspondence; Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Ethnohistorical Research Project -- Archives; Wheeler-Voegelin, Erminie, 1903-1988 -- Correspondence; Wheeler-Voegelin, Erminie, 1903-1988 -- Archives; Wheeler-Voegelin, Erminie, 1903-1988 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Voegelin, C. F. (Charles Frederick), 1906-1986 -- Correspondence; Voegelin, C. F. (Charles Frederick), 1906-1986 -- Archives; Voegelin, C. F. (Charles Frederick), 1906-1986 -- Correspondence -- Selections
- Correspondence, 1953-1965
  - United States Department of Justice, 1953-1964
    Scope and Contents
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Justice Department Correspondence (Box 1)
      - (Yost, Barney, Stewart), 1953-1954 (Box 1)
      - 1955 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1956 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1956 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1957 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1957 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1958 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1958 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1959 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1959 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Jan-Jun, 1961 (Box 1)
      - Jul-Dec, 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962 (Box 1)
      - 1963 (Box 1)
      - 1964 (Box 1)
  - Co-operation, 1956-1962
    - Co-operation (Box 1)
      - #1, 1956 (Box 1)
      - #2, 1957 (Box 1)
      - #3, 1958 (Box 1)
      - #4, 1959 (Box 1)
      - #5, 1960 (Box 1)
      - 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962 (Box 1)
  - Report required, 1955-1962 (Box 2)
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Area 242 Docket 18-c, Justice Dept. Reports Required, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Cons. N. Indiana Docket No. 254 et al., Justice Dept. Reports Required, 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence Docket 254, Justice Dept. Reports Required, 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - Ethnohistory: Cushing-Malloy and miscellaneous correspondence, 1955-1965 (Box 2)
    - General File, Justice Dept. Reports Required, 1958-1965 (Box 2)
    - (Royce) Areas 25 and 26, Justice Report Required, 1959 (Box 2)
    - (Royce) Areas 53 and 54, Justice Report Required, 1959-1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953-1967
    - Baynton-Wharton-Morgan Papers, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Conference Committee, 1954-1956 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence-Misc., 1953-1966 (Box 2)
    - Harrison Papers, WHL:RE, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Inquiries, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Ethnohistory, 1956-1967 (Box 2)
    - Klamath, Dept. of Justice, 1957-1965 (Box 2)
    - Mississippi Valley Historical Association, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    - Pit River Docket# 347, Dept. of Justice, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Royce Area 49, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Royce Areas 261, Wisc., Minn. I, 332, Minn. I and 482, Minn. I Request for Publications, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Winnebago, Department of Justice Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Yuchi, Dept. of Justice, 1957 (Box 2)
- Reports, 1953-1969
  - Area 11 (Royce) Docket 13-g et al, Department of Justice Report, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Area 66 Docket No. 59 et al., Department of Justice Report, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Area 111, Department of Justice Reports, 1958-1965 (Box 2)
  - Areas 73-74 (Royce) Docket No. 317 et al., Department of Justice, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Areas 87-88 Docket No. 13-F et al., Department of Justice Report, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Consolidated Illinois-Docket 315 Illinois, Department of Justice (Box 2)
    - from, 24 Aug 1963 (Box 2)
    - through, 24 Aug 1963 (Box 2)
    - Report, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Annual Report and Workload (Box 2)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Fox Rough Draft, undated (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research Project I, Department of Justice Final Report, 11 Aug 1964 (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research Project II, Department of Justice Final Report, 11 Aug 1964 (Box 3)
  - Klamath, Report, Department of Justice, undated (Box 3)
  - Miami Docket 253, Department of Justice, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Quarterly Progress Reports, Department of Justice, 1953-1961 (Box 3)
  - Sac Rough Draft (Re. Sauk & others at Prarie du Sac), undated (Box 3)
  - Six Nations (Martin) Docket 344, Department of Justice Report, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Research trip reports, 1955-1963
    - Cincinnati, Western Reserve Historical Society Hist. & Philos. of Ohio, Library Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Chicago, University of, Ethnohistorical Microfilm Collection, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
    - Chicago (EJB), Library Trip Report, undated (Box 3)
    - Detroit Public Library (EJB), Burton Collection, Library Trip Report, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research Project, Microfilm Holdings of Huntington Library, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Illinois State Museum - W. C. Temple, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
    - Indiana Historical Society, WM. H. Smith Memorial Library, Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Indiana State Library (EJB), Library Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Indiana University, Library, 1955-1961 (Box 3)
    - Indiana University Library, Erwin Welsch, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Kansas State Historical Society, 1955-1957 (Box 3)
    - Lilly, Library, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Marietta College Library (EJB), Library Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Michigan, University of, WM. L. Clements Library, Library Trip Report, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Missouri Historical Society (EJB), Library Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - National Archives (EJB), Library Trip Report, 1958 (Box 3)
    - National Archives and Others, Future Orders, 1957 (Box 3)
    - National Archives and Department of the Interior (HH), Library Trip Report, 1959 (Box 3)
    - New York Public Library--EWV, Library Report, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Ohio, Historical and Philosophical Society of, Library Trip Report, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Ohio, Historical Society, Ohio State Library, undated (Box 3)
    - Ottawa, Canada, Hudson's Bay Company Archives, Library Trip Report, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Price Lists and Index Sheets for Maps, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
    - Springfield and Urbana, Illinois (EJB), Library Trip Report, 1952-1959 (Box 3)
    - Illinois State Museum - W. C. Temple, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
- Subject files, 1869-1967
  - Appointments and Tenure, 1954-1960 (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Book Want Lists, 1954-1964 (Box 3)
  - Consultants, Justice, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - Directives, Department of Justice, 1954-1963 (Box 3)
  - Docket Numbers and Hearing Dates, Department of Justice, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Exhibits - Court Objections, Department of Justice, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research, Wheeler-Voegelin, Erminie, Misc., Department of Justice, 1953-1967 (Box 3)
    General
    This folder contains information on the origin of the project.
  - Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research, Wheeler-Voegelin, Misc. #2, Justice Dept., 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Greenville, Treaty of, Justice Department Klamath, Justice Dept., 1957-1965 (Box 3)
  - Klamath, Agency Letterbook of Letters Rec'd at Yainax Sub-station, Department of Justice, 21 Sep 1869 - 27 Apr 1872 (Box 3)
  - Material Loaned By Great Lakes-Ohio Valley Research Project News Releases, 1953-1954, 1957-1960 (Box 3)
  - News releases, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Personnel, Department of Justice, 1960-1964 (Box 3)
  - Project Materials (tentative), Department of Justice, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Research Contract, Justice, 1951-1965 (Box 3)
- Financial materials, 1953-1966
  The following records were selected as being representative of the financial records in this collection. Two cubic feet of related financial and payroll records were discarded when the collection was origianally processed due to their lack of historical significance. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Budget, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Budget statements from Indiana University, 1953-1959 (Box 3)
  - Microfilm Requisitions, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Purchase Order Requisitions, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Purchase Order Requisitions #1 (1-50), Aug 1953 - Jun 1954 (Box 3)
  - Purchase Order Requisitions #7, 1958-1959 (Box 3)